If you follow my advice
to eat a lot of greens daily
—and you should!—
just make sure to vary the types of greens
to avoid getting too many oxalates.
Watch the video for details.
"Kidney Stones and Oxalates in
Spinach, Chard, and Beet Greens"
Kidney stones affect as many
as 1 in 10 people in their lifetime
and can cause excruciating pain.
Makes me cross my legs
just thinking about them.
Oxalate stones are
the most common type,
forming when the oxalate
concentration in your urine gets
so high it basically crystalizes
out a solution, like rock candy.
Some foods, like spinach,
have lots of oxalates in them.
Should we try to reduce our intake
of oxalates to lower our risk?
It turns out that people who
do get stones don't seem to eat
any more oxalates on average
than people who don't get stones.
It may be less what you eat
and more what you absorb.
People who are predisposed to
kidney stones just appear to be born
with a higher intestinal
oxalate absorption.
Their guts just really suck it up.
So-called "super absorbers"
assimilate up to 50% more oxalate
than non-stone formers.
Overall, the impact of typical dietary
oxalate on the amount of oxalates
that end up in the urine
appears to be small.
Even a massive dose of dietary
oxalates typically only results
in a relatively mild increase in the
amount that makes it into your urine.
A 25-fold increase in
oxalate consumption
doesn't even double the concentration
of oxalates flowing through your kidneys,
so it's really more determined
by genetics than diet.
But still, until you get
your first stone,
how do you know if you're
a super absorber or not?
Is it safer to just generally avoid
higher oxalate fruits and veggies?
People who eat more
fruits and vegetables
may actually tend to get
fewer kidney stones.
When researchers put it to
the test and removed produce
from people's diets, their kidney
stone risk instead went up.
Removing fruits and veggies can make
your dietary oxalate intake go down,
but your body produces its own
oxalate internally as a waste product
that you may have a more
difficult time getting rid of,
without the alkalizing effects of fruits
and vegetables on your urine pH.
This may help explain why those eating
plant-based get fewer kidney stones,
but it also may be due to their
cutting animal protein intake,
which can have an acid-forming
effect in the kidneys.
We've known this for 40 years.
Just a single can of daily tuna
fish can increase your risk
of forming stones 250%, and even
just cutting back on animal protein
may help cut kidney
stone risk in half.
Surely there's some level of oxalate
intake that could put people
at risk regardless.
There have been a few rare cases
reported of people drinking green
juices and smoothies getting
oxalate kidney stones,
though most had
extenuating circumstances.
This case describes a woman
whose kidneys shut down
after a 10-day juice cleanse, which
included two cups of spinach a day.
Normally we might not expect a
cup or two of spinach to cause
such a violent reaction, but she
had two aggravating factors.
She had gastric bypass surgery, which
can increase oxalate absorption,
and a history of prolonged antibiotic use.
There's actually a friendly bacteria
you want in your colon called oxalobacter
that eats oxalate for breakfast,
leaving even less for us to absorb,
but it can get wiped out by long-term
broad spectrum antibiotic use.
She still probably wouldn't have
run into a problem though,
if she had used something
other than spinach,
or beet greens or swiss chard—
the trifecta of high-oxalate greens.
Kale has hundreds of times
less oxalates than spinach.
She would have had to have juiced
in excess of 650 cups of kale a day
to get a comparable dose, so over those
10 days, more than 6,000 cups of kale.
But are the three high oxalate
greens only a problem for people
with extenuating circumstances
or who are otherwise at high risk?
And what if you cook the greens?
How much is too much?
I'll answer those questions, next.
The tragic case in which
a green smoothie cleanse
shut down the kidneys of a woman,
who drank two cups of spinach a day
for just 10 days, is
complicated by the fact that
she had had a gastric bypass,
and was on prolonged antibiotics,
which can both increase absorption
of the oxalates in spinach.
So can taking mega-doses of vitamin C.
This guy went into kidney failure
juicing spinach and beet greens,
but he was also taking about
2,000 mg a day of vitamin C.
Vitamin C is metabolized into
oxalate inside the body
and likely played a role
in his oxalate overload.
In both cases their juicing
alone was giving them
more than 1,200 mg of oxalate a day,
which is easy with spinach—
just two cups a day—but
practically impossible
with most other greens like kale,
requiring more than six
hundred cups a day.
There is one case of apparent
dietary oxalate overload-
induced kidney failure uncomplicated
by surgery, antibiotics, or vitamin C.
A man who had lost
about 80 pounds eating
a diet of greens, berries, and nuts,
which evidently included
spinach six times a day.
Tragically, his kidney
function never recovered.
Remember that study purporting
to show a “massive” load
of dietary oxalate didn’t have
much of an effect on urine levels?
That study went up to
250 mg of oxalates a day.
That is massive if you were
talking about most greens.
That would be 25 cups
of collard greens,
60 cups of mustard greens,
125 cups of kale,
or 250 cups of bok choy at a time.
But, that’s less than
one half cup of spinach.
Spinach really is an outlier.
Even though there’s
small amounts of oxalates
found throughout the food supply,
spinach alone may account
for 40 percent of oxalate
intake in the United States.
The Harvard cohorts found
that men and older women
who ate spinach eight
or more times a month
had about a 30 percent higher risk
of developing kidney stones.
What if you cook it?
Oxalates are water soluble so,
for example, blanching collard
greens can reduce oxalate levels
by up to a third, so those 25 cups
at a time can then be 33!
For low-oxalate greens
it doesn’t matter,
cooked or not, since
they’re so low regardless.
Steaming spinach reduces
oxalate levels 30 percent
and boiling cuts oxalate
levels more than half.
Boil the three high-oxalate
greens—spinach, beet greens,
and swiss chard—and 60
percent of the oxalates
are leached into the cooking water.
They start out so high,
though, even cooked
would contain hundreds of times more
than low oxalate greens like kale.
For high-oxalate greens it
doesn’t matter, cooked or not,
since they’re so high regardless.
The bottom line is that anyone
with a history of kidney stones,
otherwise at high risk,
or who eats cups a day
should probably avoid the big three.
This is especially important for
those who juice or blend their greens,
as oxalates appear to be
absorbed more rapidly
in liquid than solid form.
Another reason to give
preference to low-oxalate greens
is that they are less
stingy with their calcium.
While less than a third of the
calcium in milks may be bioavailable,
(whether from a cow or a plant),
most of the calcium in low-oxalate
vegetables is absorbed.
The calcium bioavailability in
some greens is twice that of milk,
but the oxalates in spinach,
chard, and beet greens
bind to the calcium
preventing the absorption.
Other high-oxalate foods
that have been associated
with kidney problems at high enough
doses include chaga mushroom powder.
Four to five teaspoons a day
and you can end up on dialysis;
four cups a day of rhubarb
is also not a good idea;
more than a cup a day
of almonds, or cashews.
And then star fruit, which I
did a video in the past about:
a single dose of about a cup
and a quarter of star fruit juice,
or just four to six fruit.
Excessive tea consumption
can be a problem,
especially instant tea,
which boosts urine oxalate
nearly four times
higher than brewed tea.
Two cases of kidney damage
have been reported
both of which were attributed to
drinking a gallon of iced tea a day.
Tea, like spinach, is super healthy;
just don’t overdo it.